"Cannabis for IBD
(Inflammatory Bowel Disease)"
“Medical marijuana:
A panacea or scourge?”
For 5,000 years, cannabis has
been used throughout the world
for medicinal purposes, even
prescribed by American physicians
early on, a fact that’s
often used by medical marijuana
proponents to justify modern
medical applications.
But the field of old-timey
medicine was fraught with
patent medicine snake oil nonsense,
not to mention bloodletting
and other questionable
and harmful remedies.
Skeptics criticize the
medical marijuana movement
as the “medical excuse
marijuana movement”,
insinuating that epileptic
children and the terminally ill
are just being used as props
to Trojan horse in the
legalization of recreational use,
or to peddle outlandish claims
about “miracle cancer cures,”
frustrating researchers
in the field who just want
to get at the science.
For example, what
about the therapeutic use
of cannabis for inflammatory
bowel diseases
like Crohn’s disease
and ulcerative colitis?
Conventional therapies
mainly work by suppressing
the immune system to try to
tamp down the inflammation.
Given the limited therapy options
and known adverse side effects
from these drugs, often people
suffering these diseases ended up
having to get inflamed sections
of their bowels removed surgically,
so you can see why there’s so
much interest in alternative approaches.
About one in six IBD patients
who use marijuana say it helps
with their symptoms, so researchers
decided to put it to the test.
Thirteen patients with
inflammatory bowel disease were given
a third of a pound of marijuana
to smoke at their leisure
over a period of 3 months, and
they felt significantly better.
Now there was no control group,
so you don’t know if
they would have gotten better anyway,
or what role the placebo
effect may have played.
It’s like some of the
studies of cannabis used
for pediatric epilepsy:
response rates of over 30 percent,
seizure frequency cut in
half in a third of the kids.
That’s amazing until you
realize you can sometimes get
the same kind of amazing
response giving kids nothing,
giving them a sugar pill placebo.
That’s why it’s critical to
do randomized, double-blind,
placebo-controlled trials,
but there weren’t any
on cannabis and IBD until 2013.
Twenty-one patients with
Crohn’s disease for which nothing
seemed to help, so they
randomized them to either
smoke 2 joints a day of real
pot or a look-alike placebo pot.
And 90 percent of the subjects
in the cannabis group got better,
compared to only 40 percent
in the placebo group.
Here's a graph of their symptom scores:
no big change in the placebo
group over the two-month study,
but the cannabis group like
cut their symptoms in half.
They acknowledge that long-term
cannabis use is not without risks,
but it may be a cakewalk
compared to the potential adverse
and even life-threatening
side effects of some of the
more powerful conventional therapies,
so the study was heralded
as offering “High Hope”
for digestive disorders.
Now the study was funded by a medical
marijuana advocacy organization,
in fact the main supplier in the
country, and so there may have been
expectations placed on the subjects
on how much better this stuff
is going to make them feel
(in other words a set-up
for the placebo effect).
But they controlled for that, right?
Those getting the real stuff
did significantly better
than those randomized
to get the placebo pot.
But wait a second.
The whole point of a placebo
is to be indistinguishable
from the real thing,
so the subjects don’t know
which group they’re really in.
How do you do that with
a psychoactive drug?
You can’t, which is the problem.
They tried to hide
which group people were in
by recruiting only patients
who never tried pot before in
hopes that they wouldn’t notice,
but of course most of them did.
So what we’re left with is
basically another unblinded study.
They asked them a bunch of subjective
questions, “how you feelin’?”,
and those who mostly knew
they were taking the drug
said they were feeling better.
There was no change in the
objective lab values, like CRP,
a sign of inflammation and so
maybe the marijuana is just
masking symptoms without actually
affecting intestinal inflammation.
Another indicator that cannabis
may not be affecting the course
of the disease itself is how
quickly the symptoms rebounded.
Two weeks after the study
ended the cannabis group
was right back up to where they started.
So, no difference in objective
inflammatory markers,
and given the rapid rebound
it seems more plausible
that cannabis ameliorated
the symptoms of Crohn’s disease,
rather than actually
modulating the disease itself.
Okay, yeah, but the
symptoms are terrible.
A reduction in pain is a reduction in pain.
From the point of view of the
patients, a marked symptomatic
improvement and ability to resume
normal life is not trivial,
whether or not the inflammation
persists, unless, of course,
cannabis somehow made the
disease worse in the long run.
This survey study published the
following year found that
cannabis provided that same
immediate symptomatic relief
but was associated with a worse
disease prognosis over time.
Patients with inflammatory
bowel disease reported that
cannabis improved their pain,
cramping, and diarrhea,
but use for more than 6 months
in Crohn’s patients
appeared to be a strong predictor
of them ending up in surgery,
5 times the odds of them
ending up under the knife.
Now there’s two possible
explanations for this.
It’s quite possible that it
was the increased severity
that led to the cannabis use
and not the other way around.
But the alternative explanation is
that cannabis use may worsen
the prognosis, leading to greater
surgeries and hospitalizations.
That’s why we really need
prospective clinical trials
where we follow people over
time to see which came first,
but until then maybe we should consider
cannabis use in IBD
as potentially harmful.
Not just to err on the side
of caution, but there was
this other study on hepatitis C
patients that found
that daily cannabis use was
associated with nearly 7 times
the odds of worse liver fibrosis,
which is like scar tissue.
And so hey, if cannabis really
does make fibrosis worse,
then that could potentially explain
why cannabis users with IBD
may be more likely to end up
on the operating table.